Guide to the Hapgood Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Hapgood family papers
1789-1860
MS 795
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
The papers consist chiefly of the letters of Jonathan Grout and of his son-in-law, Hutchins Hapgood, to their respective sons. The letters of Jonathan Grout are mainly about the family business which his son was managing while Jonathan Grout, Sr., was in Congress (1789-1792). Only a few letters allude to politics, one on the building of the Capitol in Washington and another on the national debt. The letters of Hutchins Hapgood are also concentrated on finances and business activities, but include passages of advice to his sons about their education and health. Two letters from Hutchins Hapgood, Jr., discuss New York City and a yellow fever epidemic in the city. Also in the papers are letters by various other family members.
Hapgood family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elizabeth H. Backman, 1977.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence and a few other items, 1789-1860, of the related Hapgood and Grout families of Petersham, Massachusetts, make up this small collection. The major correspondents are Jonathan Grout, Sr., and Hutchins Hapgood, Sr., and their children. The papers are arranged alphabetically by author.
Jonathan Grout's twenty-two letters date from the time of his service in the First Congress, 1789-1792, but refer only occasionally to Congressional activities; see, for example, the letter of 1789 Sep 6 on the building of the Capitol in Washington, and the letter of 1790 Jan 18 on the funding of the National Debt. The bulk of his letters to his son deal with family business and other matters which Jonathan Grout, Jr., was handling in his father's absence, as do Jonathan Grout, Jr.'s two letters to his father. The three letters of Jonathan Grout, Sr., to Hutchins Hapgood are also concerned with business.
The fifty letters of Hutchins Hapgood, Sr., to his sons Hutchins and Charles cover the period 1809 through 1827; two copies of his will (1825 Jan 28, 1837 Oct 3) are also included. The letters contain advice to his sons about their education and health, and comments on politics and current events, but deal for the most part with his own and Hutchins Hapgood, Jr.'s business activities and financial problems, including land purchases, the settlement of the estates of family members, and several law suits. A few letters from Hutchins Hapgood, Sr.'s children and his daughter-in-law Betsy Hopkins deal with family matters. Two letters from Hutchins Hapgood, Jr., also discuss the Dutch community of Harlem and New York City and a yellow fever epidemic in the city (1822 Sep 16, 1826 May 31).
The remaining items in the collection include receipts, notes, and letters pertaining to the Grout and Hapgood families; one of these letters; from Abner Morse (1860 Nov 23), deals with Hapgood family genealogy.
These papers were donated to Yale University by Elizabeth H. Backman in 1977.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Jonathan Grout family, and a biography of the Hapgood family, please consult the Genealogical Chart and Biography.
Business; Families; Fathers and sons; Yellow fever -- New York (State) -- New York; New England; New York (N.Y.) -- Description and travel; United States -- Politics and government; Businessmen; Legislators; Politicians; Grout, Jonathan, 1737-1807; Grout, Jonathan, 1763-1835; Hapgood, Hutchins, 1763-1837; Hapgood, Hutchins, 1792-1828; Hinds, Maria Hapgood, 1798-1842; Hapgood family
- Inventory, 1789-1860; 0.25; (1 box)
  - BREWER, Sally: receipts for board and room, to Jonathan Grout, member of first Federal U.S. Congress, (3 items), 9 February 1792, one of undated, and 14 January 1793 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - GROUT, Jonathan (U.S. Congressman)
    - Manuscript list of battles of Revolutionary War, in his own handwriting (1 item) (Box 1, Folder 2A)
    - ALS, Boston,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 31 January 1789 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 11 May 1789 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 5 July 1789 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 9 July 1789 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 12 July 1789 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 2 August 1789 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 6 September 1789 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 18 January 1790 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 17 February 1790 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 14 March 1790 (Box 1, Folder 2B)
    - ALS, [?],, to his son Jonathan Jr., March 1790 (Box 1, Folder 2B)
    - ALS, New York,, to Lt. Hutchins Hapgood, 28 April 1790 (Box 1, Folder 2B)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 30 May 1790 (Box 1, Folder 2B)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 6 June 1790 (Box 1, Folder 2B)
    - ALS, New York,, to Hutchins Hapgood, 27 June 1790 (Box 1, Folder 2B)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 1 July 1790 (Box 1, Folder 2B)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 15 July 1790 (Box 1, Folder 2B)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 9 December 1790 (Box 1, Folder 2B)
    - ALS, Philadelphia,, to Hutchins Hapgood, 3 January 1791 (Box 1, Folder 2B)
    - ALS, Lunenburg, Massachusetts,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 23 September 1791 (Box 1, Folder 2B)
    - ALS, New York,, to his son Jonathan Jr., 16 June 1792 (Box 1, Folder 2B)
  - GROUT, Jonathan Jr.
    - Letter unsigned, Petersham,, to his father, 28 March 1790 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter unsigned, Petersham, Massachusetts,, to his father, 6 April 1790 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - HAPGOOD, Betsy (Hopkins): ALS, Petersham,, to her brother-in-law Hutchins Hapgood, 11 January 1824 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - HAPGOOD, Eliza: ALS, Petersham, 16 October 1825 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - HAPGOOD, George: ALS, Warren, Ohio,, to his cousin Mrs. Arathusa Howe, 19 January 1824 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - HAPGOOD, Hutchins (Postmaster, Petersham, Massachusetts)
    - ADS, Receipt, Petersham,, to Jonathan Grout, 8 May 1792 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., at New Salem Academy, 22 April 1809 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., at Dartmouth College, 8 May 1811 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., at Dartmouth College, 19 May 1811 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 17 November 1811 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 26 April 1812 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 4 August 1812 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 6 November 1812 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 30 October 1817 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 21 March 1818 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 14 August 1820 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 11 March 1821 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - ALS, Petersham, 11 Nov 1821, to his son Hutchins Jr. (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 25 November 1821 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 2 December 1821 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 3 July 1822 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 7 July 1822 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 20 March 1823 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 21 April1823 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 18 May 1823 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 7 July 1823 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 14 July 1823 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Charles., 16 July 1823 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 28 July 1823 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 4 August 1823 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Charles, at New Salem Academy, 7 September 1823 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 10 April 1824 (Box 1, Folder 6A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 3 May 1824 (Box 1, Folder 6A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 18 May 1824 (Box 1, Folder 6A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 26 May 1824 (Box 1, Folder 6A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 7 August 1824 (Box 1, Folder 6A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 26 August 1824 (Box 1, Folder 6A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 27 August 1821 (Box 1, Folder 6A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 21 November 1824 (Box 1, Folder 6A)
    - ADS, Petersham, Will, 28 January 1825 (Box 1, Folder 6A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 27 March 1825 (Box 1, Folder 6A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 30 May 1825 (Box 1, Folder 6A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 29 July 1825 (Box 1, Folder 6A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Charles, at Deerfield Academy, 22 August 1825 (Box 1, Folder 6A)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 16 October 1825 (Box 1, Folder 6B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 12 December 1825 (Box 1, Folder 6B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 27 December 1825 (Box 1, Folder 6B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 8 April 1826 (Box 1, Folder 6B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins, Jr., 14 May 1826 (Box 1, Folder 6B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 31 May 1826 (Box 1, Folder 6B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 5 June 1826 (Box 1, Folder 6B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Charles, at Deerfield Academy, 30 August 1826 (Box 1, Folder 6B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Hutchins Jr., 10 February 1826 (Box 1, Folder 6B)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his son Charles, at New Salem Academy, 2 October 1827 (Box 1, Folder 6B)
    - Will (attested copy), Petersham, 1837 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 6B)
  - HAPGOOD, Hutchins, Jr.
    - ALS, Claverack, New York,, to his brother Seth, 11 May 1816 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ALS, New York,, to his father, 11 November 1818 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ALS, New York,, to his father, 29 December 1820 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ALS, New York,, to his father, 16, 17 September 1822 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ALS New York,, to his father, 31 May 1826 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - HAPGOOD, Seth: Draft of a letter of recommendation to the U.S. Postmaster General, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - HAPGOOD, Thomas
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his brother Hutchins Jr., 31 December 1815 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to his brother Hutchins Jr., 17 February 1818 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - HINDS, Maria (Hapgood)
    - ALS, Petersham,, to her brother Hutchins Jr., 22 February 1816 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ALS, Harvard, Massachusetts,, to her brother, Hutchins Jr., 15 January 1826 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - JACKSON, Thomas: ADS,, to Town of Petersham, 9 June 1783 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - MORSE, Abner: ALS, Boston,, to Seth Hapgood, 23 November 1860 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - POWERS, Fanny C.: ALS, Cazenovia, New York,, to her father, in French; inside letter, in English, to her mother, 9 August 1851 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - THOMAS, S. B.: PDS, (Worcester, Massachusetts), 28 February 1829 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - WEED, I. (attorney): ALS, Coxsackie, New York,, to Hutchins Hapgood, Jr., 22 August 1825 (Box 1, Folder 9)